Good morning, and we have a lot of topics to cover.
You have the book here on principles.
And my book, which I looks like I might have,
oh, here it is, has a few little marks in it.
And I encourage each of you to use little post-its
while you're reading the book from that standpoint.
And I thought, Ray, we'd start with a little bit.
Why did you go into finance?
I caddied in the 1960s when I was 12.
I caddied at a golf course.
And everybody was talking about the stock market then.
It was the stock market had gone up for a long, long time.
And if you were to get a haircut or anything,
you would always be talking about stocks.
And so I took my cadding money.
I learned $6 a bag, and so I'd get $12 a round.
And I took my cadding money.
And I put it in the stock market.
I mean, I was curious.
And I remember the first stock I bought was accompanied
by the name of Northeast Airlines.
And the only reason I bought it is because it was selling
for less than $5 a share.
And I figured I could buy more shares,
so I'd make more money if it went up.
That was my brilliant theory.
Of course, it was dumb.
But it was a company that was about to go bankrupt.
Somebody acquired it, it tripled, and I was hooked.
So I got hooked on the markets at that time.
I was trading in the debt of Northeast Airlines
at that time, and.
Really?
How cool.
And we were debating shorting the stock.
Our long position, the debt was selling
at a substantial discount.
And I think the time that Ray's talking about,
if you ever want to check an archive,
there was a book published, Happiness
is a Stock that Doubles in a Year.
And this was a period of time where
if you couldn't make 50% or 100% of your money,
you really weren't doing a good job.
And it looked at the American Stock Exchange
and all the stocks that doubled during this period
of time in a year.
And it basically concluded you should be focused
on very low price stocks.
So that book symbolized that issue.
Let's talk a little bit about your family
and how your life growing up potentially influenced you later.
Well, my dad was a jazz musician.
And my mom was a stay-at-home mom.
My dad played late at night.
And he's a good man, but I didn't have a lot of contact
with him until later.
And I was just a normal kid.
We played touch football on the streets.
My mom loved me a lot.
I was lucky to have a really good family with a lot of love.
I don't know.
You know, there was a lot of work done on education
looking back in the 60s and 70s.
And one of the conclusions was the most important thing
in education was having two parents that loved you enough
and expressed confidence and good teachers.
Yes, that was my circumstances.
And you're exactly right.
And when I contrasted with some of the circumstances
of others, like I was ultra-rich in being
able to have two parents who loved me
and to be able to go to a school in which I was well-educated
and to have, then, an environment which was also
inspirational in that it was an aspirational environment.
It was the time when John Kennedy was going to go
to the moon and were going to eliminate poverty.
And the United States was the richest country
in the world, counting 40% of world GDP.
And that whole aspirational opportunity,
the idea of equal opportunity and a great abundance of it
in our parents, where you would do better than your parents,
it was a different kind of environment then.
And so what Ray's talking a little bit about
are the baby boomers.
Now, Ray is much younger than I,
but he's still in that baby boomer group today.
And this group that was born 1946 to 1964
and much different generation than our parents,
our parents' success was really highly
dependent on the government, whether it was World War II,
whether it was the Depression.
And our parents told those baby boomers,
you could be anything.
One person can change the world.
And in 1964, the first year, the baby boomers
went to college from that standpoint.
If we step back and think about that period of time, Ray,
I was at Berkeley and taking these courses
in quantum economics, et cetera, was the only person
that enjoyed it in a class.
And I think, and every, I was excited
because it was like a chapter, a story.
In every class, we got new algebraic formulas
on how the world worked that we could write,
put in, and our computers, our 360 was about
as big as this room at that time.
And when I think about the book and many
of the principles you put forth, I think about
the advancements in technology, computing power today
versus us writing those little algorithms every class
to try to define what was happening in the world.
And in many ways, your effort to create a meritocracy
is based somewhat on those little formulas
that we had written down in that class at Berkeley.
Take us through that concept.
Well, I mean, yeah, you remember it well, like you say.
And we had those little punch cards, right?
And you would drop them in.
And then I learned what regression analysis was, right?
Well, and that was the key to discovering everything.
You just put the data in and you got
the two independent variables and then explained it
and then you understood it.
But at the time, yeah, I mean, literally,
I would have colored pens and rulers to plot my graphs,
literally operating that way.
But, and then I remember when I started my business,
you know, which was in 1975, I had an HP67 calculator.
So you put the little thing in and you type in
and you got the regressions and that's
where it started, right?
But yeah, for you and for me, I guess, you speak for you,
I then began to understand that we could put things
in equations and we could put our thinking in equations.
And algorithms, they were called equations then.
They're algorithms now.
They're basically the same things.
And then you could have the computer
start to think in parallel with you.
And that's when it began.
So I would say it the opposite way though.
It wasn't that that thinking led me
to have an idea of meritocracy.
It was that I wanted to have an idea of meritocracy
for other reasons, I'll explain,
that then made me use the algorithms
to help me do that.
In particular, look, in order to be successful
in the markets, you have to be an independent thinker
who bets against the consensus
because the consensus is in the price.
And also, nobody's good enough to know themselves
that they can, all the answers.
So I learned by having, you know,
the shit kicked out of me a fair amount of time.
I learned a certain amount of humility.
And then I knew that I didn't have enough
of the right answers.
So I wanted a bunch of independent thinkers.
And so when you get independent thinkers,
then how do you get past that?
And you're gonna wanna have
an idea meritocratic process.
And then what I found is that algorithms
allowed me to do that because rather than think
about what decision we were gonna make
at any point in time, we would think about
what the criteria for making the decisions would be.
And then if you write down those criteria
and make them clear and then put them
in the form of an algorithm,
then you could test how they would have worked over history.
And that allowed idea meritocratic thinking.
And we also had a ways of getting past it.
I'm sure we'll get into those.
I don't wanna hijack that by explaining those ways.
But that led us to make, use algorithms
to have an idea meritocracy,
to make better decisions than any individuals could.
And that's been really the key to the success.
It's one of the, it's in the work principles here.
And it's that one of those things
that I really wanna emphasize.
Cause I think we're now in an era
in which when we talk about open source and such things,
we're now in an era where idea meritocratic thinking
can be then systemized to produce better results
than any individual can produce.
So let's talk just a bit of specific,
then I'll go back in time.
I'm home watching the election in November results come out.
And as the results come out, things are changing
and it appears at the moment that President Trump
is about to be elected.
And the stock market in
a,